Finding Aid for Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology (University of Michigan) records, 1901-1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology (University of Michigan) records 1901-1995 1935-1958 1980-1990
University of Michigan. Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology.
921084 Bimu C500 2
Records include registers; annual reports; administrative files; departmental minutes; admissions books containing details on admission, births, treatment, and disposition of patients; and photographs.
6.5 linear feet in 8 boxes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Records received in 1990 and 1994 from the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology (Donor No. 7883 ).
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy.
The Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 8
Patient/Client Records -- 2, 3, 8
The history of the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology parallels the history of the Medical School at the University of Michigan. Each dates from modest beginnings in 1850 and, after a series of travails in the nineteenth century, most fully realized their potential in the twentieth century. In the early years instruction was handled by Abram Sager and Alonzo Benjamin Palmer, each of whom taught other medical courses. As time passed medicine became more scientific and specialized, and the department came to offer more specific instruction. Edward Swift Dunster succeeded Sager in 1874 and oversaw the extension of Ob/Gyn lectures to a two-year course. Dunster saw his lectures as the basic foundation of medical education, but he was thwarted in his attempts to offer clinical instruction by the paucity of hospital births in Ann Arbor. James Nelson Martin, who came to head the department upon the death of Dunster in 1888, was similarly frustrated in his efforts to offer clinical experience to his interns.
It was not until the tenure of Reuben Peterson as chair of the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology (1901-1931) that clinical instruction came to be a meaningful, integral part of instruction to aspiring Ob/Gyns. The rise of this sort of clinical instruction at the University of Michigan postdates its general use in American medical education; this owes more to the small-town nature of Ann Arbor than to any hide-bound medical practices of medical professors. Even with Peterson's tireless lobbying for more clinical, hands-on experience in maternity wards, it was not until 1910 that the Ob/Gyn interns saw as many as 100 births in any one year. After establishing the importance of clinical instruction (and insuring its practical use), Peterson then worked to have the Maternity Hospital made safer from sepsis. He finally succeeded in 1925 when the Maternity Ward opened in the new University Hospital, thus temporarily fulfilling the department's long-standing needs.
After Peterson's retirement in 1931, Norman F. Miller headed the department until 1964. In 1950 Miller oversaw the department's move to the new Women's Hospital which at the time "provided all available facilities for obstetrics as well as gynecology." Once again, time and changing medical practices outstripped the existing plant. During the chairmanship of J. Robert Willson (1964-1978) gynecology was handled in the main hospital, the Holden Perinatal Center was established to deal with high-risk pregnancies and newborn intensive care cases, and the department affiliated with Wayne County General Hospital to insure that students would acquire sufficient clinical experience. In 1990 Women's Hospital was moved to a new building to meet the contemporary needs of patients and doctors.
For a more detailed history of the University of Michigan Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology consult Obstetrics, Gynecology and the University of Michigan, by Richard W. Stander and Warren H. Pearse (privately published c. 1967). For information on the department during the tenure of J. Robert Willson (1964-1978), consult Willson's 1992 account, "The Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology at the University of Michigan Medical School, 1964-1978," which is included with Willson's personal papers.
1850-1874 Abram Sager
1874-1888 Edward S. Dunster
1888-1891 James N. Martin (acting)
1891-1901 James N. Martin
1901-1931 Rueben Peterson
1931-1963 Norman F. Miller
1964-1978 J. Robert Willson
1978-1979 George Morley (interim)
1979-1983 Alan Beer
1983-1985 Rudi Ansbacher (acting)
1985-1991 Preston V. Dilts
1991-1993 Rudi Ansbacher (interim)
1993- Timothy R.B. Johnson
The records of the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology document the evolution and development of this department, although the documentation is far from complete. The records primarily cover two periods: 1935-1958, and 1980-1995. The records are organized into nine series: Annual Reports; Minutes; Admissions Books/Birth Records; Registers and Miscellaneous Records; Administrative Files; Medical School Review Committee; Printed Material and Photographs.
Subjects:
Gynecology.; Hospitals--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Obstetrics.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Obstetrics and Gynecology.; University of Michigan. Hospitals.; Women's health services.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Physicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Obstetrics and Gynecology.; University of Michigan. Hospitals.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Annual reports.; Pamphlets.; Directories.; Manuals.; Programs.
- Annual Reports 1985-1994
  The Annual Reports series, documents departmental activity, summarizing significant achievements for the period from 1985/86 to 1993/94. Reports for the years 1959-1978 are to be found in the papers of J. Robert Willson who served as chairman of the department from 1964 to 1978.
  - 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - 1986-1987 (Box 1)
  - 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - 1993-1994 (Box 1)
- Minutes 1950-1958, 1980-1990
  The series, Minutes contains two separate runs of minutes. The first run, covering 1950-1958, provides rich insight into the teaching and clinical activities of the department through notes on the twice-weekly meetings of staff. As these minutes are virtually contemporaneous with the peak years of the baby boom and the first generation of hospital birthing, they are especially interesting to historians. The second run covers the decade 1980-1990, and documents a department in transition operating under three different chairmen during this period.
  - Ob/Gyn Departmental Proceedings 1950-1958
    - 1950 (May-December) (Box 1)
    - 1951 (Box 1)
    - 1952 (Box 1)
    - 1953 (Box 1)
    - 1954 (Box 1)
    - 1955 (Box 1)
    - 1956 (Box 1)
    - 1957 (Box 1)
    - 1958 (January-April) (Box 1)
  - Ob/Gyn Faculty Meeting Minutes 1980-1990
    - 1980 (Box 1)
    - 1981 (Box 1)
    - 1982 (Box 1)
    - 1983 (Box 1)
    - 1984 (Box 1)
    - 1985 (Box 1)
    - 1986 (Box 1)
    - 1987 (Box 1)
    - 1988 (Box 1)
    - 1989 (Box 1)
    - 1990 (Box 1)
- Admissions Books 1935-1961
  - Birth Records 1935-1955
    Admissions Books, dating from 1935 to 1961, consists of ten ledgers of patient records which give details on admission, births, treatment, and disposition of patients within the department. The information in the first four volumes, titled Birth Records, was evidently compiled monthly and includes data on: name and age of mother, date and time of admission, method of delivery, episiotomy, doctor, discharge date; name, sex and birthweight of child, Kahn test, circumcision, discharge date, weight, and to whom, and complications. The monthly figures aggregate much of this data as well as provide information on average length of hospitalization. The information in the last six volumes, titled Annual Ledgers) was evidently entered as the patients were treated. These volumes contain further data on: length of pregnancy and labor, rupture of membranes, type of analgesia/ anesthesia, and a franker set of comments on complications. These records are closed for 100 years from the date of creation in order to protect patient's right of privacy. Please see "Patient Record Access Restriction Policies" for further information regarding these restrictions.
    - June 1935-May 1940, 1 volumes (Box 2)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2040 ]
    - June 1940-June 1945, 1 volumes (Box 2)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2045 ]
    - July 1945-June 1950, 1 volumes (Box 2)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2050 ]
    - July 1950-July 1955, 1 volumes (Box 2)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2055 ]
  - Annual Ledgers circa 1940-1959
    - 1952, 1 volumes (Box 3)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2052 ]
    - 1953, 1 volumes (Box 3)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2053 ]
    - 1954, 1 volumes (Box 3)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2054 ]
    - 1955, 1 volumes (Box 3)
    - 1956, 1 volumes (Box 3)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2056 ]
    - 1961, 1 volumes (Box 3)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2061 ]
- Registers and Miscellaneous Records circa 1940-1959
  Registers and Miscellaneous Records, is an artificial series created around several "historical" files. These items date from the 1940s and 1950s although the information contained in the registers and lists dates from 1901 to 1979. Records include registers of visiting physicians, staff lists, clippings and material relating to the construction of the Women's Hospital in 1950, and brief notes on the activities of the Detroit and Michigan Ob/Gyn Societies.
  - Record of Visiting Physicians 1905-1944 (Box 4)
    (includes Staff Lists, 1901-1942)
  - Guest Register 1942-1967 (Box 4)
    (includes records of Michigan and Detroit Ob/Gyn societies)
  - Staff Lists 1931-1979 (Box 4)
  - Canadian Travel Club Program 1948 (Box 4)
  - Detroit Ob/Gyn Society 1937-1940 (Box 4)
  - Women's Hospital (mainly clippings) 1946-1951 (Box 4)
  - Radio Talk: "What Is This Thing Called Change of Life?," Norman F. Miller 1952 (Box 4)
  - Sager, Dunster, Martin (student paper) circa 1950 (Box 4)
- Administrative Files 1980-1994
  The Administrative Files series contains more contemporary documentation on the department, dating from 1980 to 1994, although the bulk of the material dates from 1985 to 1990. These records document resident training and the affiliated hospitals program, the department's physical facilities, as well as the development of departmental lectureships (Gosling Lectureship) and professorships (Norman F. Miller and J. Robert Willson professorships). Of note are the retreats which detail the relationship of the department to the overall Medical Center.
  - Alan Beer appointment 1978 (Box 8)
  - Budget (correspondence) 1985-1990, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Council on Graduate Medical Education 1990-1991
    - "Reexamination of the Adequacy of Physician Supply Made in 1980 by the Graduate Medical Education National Advisory Committee (GMENAC) for Six Physician Specialties," 1990 (Box 4)
  - Consultant Review (Evelyn Eskin/Health Power Associates) 1988 (Box 4)
  - Corner Health Center (Ypsilanti, Michigan) 1990
    - Annual Reports 1986/87-1991/92 (Box 4)
  - Council on Resident Education in Obstetrics and Gynecology (CREOG) Surveys 1989-1992 (Box 4)
  - Dunster (Edward Swift) Award 1988 (Box 4)
  - Ethics Curriculum 1986-1991 (Box 4)
  - Faculty Retreat 1984 (Box 4)
  - Family Practice 1985-1989, 2 folders
    - Family Practice-Ob/Gyn Task Force 1982-1983 (Box 4)
  - Five Year Plan 1988 (Box 4)
  - Foote Hospital (Jackson, Michigan) 1989-1990 (Box 4)
  - Gosling Lectureship 1990-1991, 2 folders (Box 4)
    (includes photographs)
  - GRAMEC (Grand Rapids Area Medical Education Center) Ob/Gyn Council 1985-1987 (Box 5)
  - Gynecology Clinic
    - Pain Clinic/PMS Clinic 1986-1989 (Box 5)
    - Pediatric-Adolescent Clinic 1986-1989 (Box 5)
  - Gynecology Division
    - Meetings 1985-1988, 1990 (Box 5)
    - Inpatient Admissions Issues (8A) 1987-1991 (Box 5)
    - Outpatient Services 1986 (Box 5)
    - Retreat 1990 (Box 5)
    - Sexual Abuse 1986, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Gynecology-Endocrine Lab 1986-1989 (Box 5)
  - Henry Ford Hospital 1986-1990 (Box 5)
  - Henry Ford-University of Michigan Liaison Committee 1985-1990 (Box 5)
  - Invitro Fertilization and Embryo Transfer Program 1985 (Box 5)
  - Johnson, Timothy R.B.
    - Chairman Search Commentary and Recruitment (copies) 1991-1993 (Box 8)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2023 ]
    - Legal Actions 1975-1982 (Includes patient record information (Box 8)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2082 ]
  - Joint Commission on Accreditation of Healthcare Organizations 1986-1990, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - King/Chavez/Parks Visiting Professor (Ezra Davidson) 1990 (Box 5)
  - McPherson Hospital (Howell, Michigan) 1989 (Box 5)
  - MCHC (Maternal & Child Health Care Center)
    - General 1984-1990, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Analysis of Demand for Maternal & Child Health Care Services 1986 (Box 5)
    - Antepartum/Postpartum Design Data 1986 (Box 5)
    - Dedication and Ground Breaking 1987, 1990 (Box 5)
    - Education/Conference Design Data 1986 (Box 5)
    - IVF/ET Lab Design Data 1986 (Box 5)
    - Labor and Delivery Design Data 1986 (Box 5)
    - Ob/Gyn Clinic Design Data 1986 (Box 5)
    - Ob/Gyn Faculty Offices Design Data 1986 (Box 5)
  - M-CARE Health Maintenance Organization
    - Establishment 1986-1987 (Box 5)
    - Credentialing Process 1986-1987 (Box 5)
    - Policy Regarding Reimbursement 1987-1990 (Box 5)
    - Satellite Services 1988-1990 (Box 5)
  - Mott Renewal 1990-1991, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Medical Center Retreats (Box 6)
    - Strategic Planning Retreat 1985, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Planning Retreat 1987 (Box 6)
    - Retreat 1988 (Box 6)
    - Retreat 1989 (Box 6)
  - Michigan Department of Public Health: Task Force on Infant Mortality 1986-1987 (Box 6)
  - Michigan State Medical Society 1988-1989 (Box 6)
  - Norman F. Miller Gynecological Society 1983-1990 (Box 6)
  - Norman F. Miller Professorship of Gynecology 1985-1990 (Box 6)
  - Nurse Midwifery Services 1985-1990, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Nurse Midwifery Establishment (1972) 1990 (Box 6)
  - Obstetrics
    - OB Letter (Rotational Service) 1988 (Box 6)
    - Labor and Delivery Statistics 1984-1989 (Box 6)
    - Report, "An Operational and Capacity Analysis for the Labor and Delivery Unit," 1987 (Box 6)
  - Operating Rooms 1985-1990
    - Admissions Day Surgical Program (ADP) 1985 (Box 6)
  - Perinatal Outreach Program 1990 (Box 6)
  - Postgraduate Courses 1985-1988 (Box 6)
  - Preventive Health Care Contract Report 1984-1985, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Preventive Medicine 1987 (Box 6)
  - Referring Physician
    - Referring Physician Communication 1982-1984 (Box 6)
    - Report 1986 (Box 6)
    - Advisory Council on Communication and Services 1989 (Box 6)
    - Program Planning: Survey Results 1988 (Box 6)
  - Roster of Residents and Fellows Completing Training in Obstetrics Gynecology at University of Michigan 1964-1994 (Box 7)
  - St. Joseph Mercy Hospital
    - General 1984-1990 (Box 7)
    - Integration 1984-1988 (Box 7)
    - Residency Review Application 1983 (Box 7)
    - Residency Review Application 1988 (Box 7)
  - Sager Lectureship
    - 1986 (Box 7)
    - 1987 (Box 7)
    - 1988 (Box 7)
    - 1989 (Box 7)
      (includes paper "The Legacy of Abram Sager," by Tommy N. Evans)
    - 1990 (Box 7)
    - 1991 (Box 7)
  - Ultrasound 1985-1990, 4 folders
    - Statistics 1988-1991 (Box 7)
  - Washtenaw County Ob/Gyn Society 1985-1990 (Box 7)
  - Westland Medical Center 1985, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - J. Robert Willson Professorship 1985-1989 (Box 7)
  - Women's Health Care Survey 1986-1988 (Box 7)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series, consists of portraits of individual interns and residents from 1965 to 1979 arranged chronologically by year of matriculation, prints and negatives recording the construction of the Women's Hospital in 1950, and miscellaneous staff photographs. One photograph, in poor condition, includes the departmental staff from 1904 and features Drs. Peterson and Parmeter.
  - Staff (group shot including Drs. Peterson and Parmeter) 1904 (Box 7)
  - Women's Hospital circa 1947-1950 (Box 7)
  - Individuals (Residents and Fellows) 1965-1979, 15 folders (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous undated (Box 7)
- Medical School Review Committee 1995 (Box 7)
  The Medical School Review Committee series includes a copy of the committees report as well as notes on committee meetings in which the strengths, weaknesses and needs of various Medical School departments are discussed. Department chairman Dr. Timothy Johnson headed the review committee.
  - Final Report 1995 (Box 7)
  - Committee Meeting Notes and Draft Report 1995 (Box 7)
- Printed Material
  The Printed Materials series includes brochures, invitations, practitioner directories, and a program from the departmental reunion of 1956. There is also an obstetric manual from 1923/24 which accompanied a demonstration course.
  - Unit Publications
    - Brochures and Invitations 1987 (Box 7)
    - Bulletins
      - Residency in Obstetrics and Gynecology, circa 1986 (Box 7)
    - Directories undated (Box 7)
    - Lectures
      - Sager Lecture
        - The Sesquicentennial Years of Obstetrics and Gynecology at Michigan by George W. Morley, M.D., 2000 (Box 7)
    - Manuals
      - Demonstration Course in Obstetrics, 1923/24 (Box 7)
    - Newsletters
      - Ob/Gyn Communicator: Norman F. Miller Society News and Ob/Gyn Departmental Notes, circa 1994 (Box 7)
    - Programs
      - Departmental Reunion, 1956 (Box 7)
      - Ethics, Humanities and Law in Obstetrics and Gynecology, 1989 (Box 7)
    - Statistics
      - UMMC Obstetrics and Gynecology Faculty Retreat: Environmental Assessment, 1993 (Box 7)
Related Material
Other materials related to obstetrics and gynecology can be found in the papers of Reuben Peterson and J. Robert Willson and in the records of the Ann Arbor Private Hospital which document women's health in Ann Arbor from 1902 to 1933. Use of the latter materials is also governed by the "Patient Record Access Agreement" of the Bentley Historical Library.